<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Panic! at the Kernel</title>
    <link>https://liranv.github.io/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Panic! at the Kernel</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-EN</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 04:42:12 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://liranv.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Booting Memtest86 with UEFI</title>
      <link>https://liranv.github.io/post/booting-memtest86-uefi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 04:42:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://liranv.github.io/post/booting-memtest86-uefi/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For a very long time I&amp;rsquo;ve been using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.memtest.org&#34;&gt;Memtest86+&lt;/a&gt; (Memtest86 fork) to test RAM modules.&lt;br /&gt;
Whether I was overcloking my own PC, debugging blue screens or instabilities, this was my go-to tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original Memtest86 was developed by a man named Chris Brady, but was later purchased by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.passmark.com&#34;&gt;PassMark Software&lt;/a&gt;,
and now being actively developed by them.
Memtest86+ on the other hand seems to be abandoned by now, with the latest release date being September 27, 2013.
Unlike Memtest86+, Memtest86 is a non open-source software, luckily PassMark still offers a free version with most of the needed
features included (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.memtest86.com/features.htm&#34;&gt;feature table&lt;/a&gt;).
So for the last few years I&amp;rsquo;ve been using Memtest86, and I get the impression it&amp;rsquo;s working as good, if not better
than Memtest86+ while providing better support for new hardware (e.g., DDR4), and most importantly, provides an EFI version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;let-s-get-down-to-business&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s Get Down to Business&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often times I would boot Memtest86 from a USB drive or even a CD in the ancient days.
This was fine for booting Memtest86 on machines other than mine.
But flashing a USB drive with Memtest86 every time I needed it was just a waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we do better? Sure we can! Booting directly into Memtest86 from the bootloader without any external media.&lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;rsquo;m running Archlinux and using &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/systemd-boot&#34;&gt;systemd-boot&lt;/a&gt; as my bootloader,
I find it to be easy to configure and keeping things simple.
In case you&amp;rsquo;re using a different &lt;strong&gt;UEFI supported&lt;/strong&gt; bootloader you&amp;rsquo;ll need to figure
out how to manage the boot entry for the Memtest86 efi file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we&amp;rsquo;ll need to fetch Memtest86 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.memtest86.com/downloads/memtest86-iso.tar.gz&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
and then set a bootloader entry for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;# Download and extract archive
curl -O http://www.memtest86.com/downloads/memtest86-iso.tar.gz
mkdir memtest86
tar -zxvf memtest86-iso.tar.gz -C memtest86

# Extract iso
# I&#39;m using 7z from p7zip package but you can also mount the iso to pull the files
cd memtest86
7z x Memtest86-7.2.iso

# Move the efi file to our boot partition
mv ./EFI/BOOT/BOOTX64.EFI /boot/EFI/Boot/memtest.efi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to place an entry config for the bootloader to read.
With systemd-boot, all we need to do is to create a new file like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;memtest-conf&#34;&gt;memtest.conf&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;# This file should be located at /boot/loader/entries/memtest.conf

title	Memtest86
efi	EFI/Boot/memtest.efi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that done we can now reboot the system and behold a new entry on the bootloader&amp;rsquo;s menu,
choosing it should boot directly to Memtest86.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;remarks&#34;&gt;Remarks:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This method should work with any efi file you might want to boot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;code&gt;efi&lt;/code&gt; path in the entry conf file is relative to the ESP (EFI System Partition).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things like certain paths might vary with time or on different systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>booting up</title>
      <link>https://liranv.github.io/post/bootingup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 22:50:30 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://liranv.github.io/post/bootingup/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;hello-world&#34;&gt;Hello, World!&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://liranv.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 21:42:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://liranv.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-blog&#34;&gt;The Blog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After playing with some static-site-generators and having a long lasting urge for writing my own blog, I&amp;rsquo;ve
finally decided to make it happen.
This blog is mainly about me sharing my experiences and 2¢ on my voyage in the sea of awesome tech.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://liranv.github.io/license/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://liranv.github.io/license/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;code&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;MIT License

Copyright (c) 2016 Liran Vaknin

Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
of this software and associated documentation files (the &amp;quot;Software&amp;quot;), to deal
in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights
to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all
copies or substantial portions of the Software.

THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED &amp;quot;AS IS&amp;quot;, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
SOFTWARE.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;non-code&#34;&gt;Non-Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;license&#34; href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Creative Commons License&#34; style=&#34;border-width:0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc/4.0/88x31.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This work is licensed under a &lt;a rel=&#34;license&#34; href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>